# **Ryan Parman**

Cloud-native engineering leader with a focus on reliability, scalability, and security for the modern web.

Links: GitHub (personal) • GitHub (side project) • LinkedIn • Stack Overflow • Role-targeted résumés

Format: Web • PDF • Word • OpenDocument • Raw Markdown

# Summary

Ryan Parman is a cloud-native engineering leader with over 25 years of experience, who specializes in technical leadership, software development, site reliability engineering, and cybersecurity for the modern web. A seasoned problem-solver who excels at listening, adapting, and driving continuous improvement. Committed to delivering exceptional work, building impactful solutions, and elevating team performance.

# **Work Experience**

Older roles are truncated for brevity. If interested, details can be found on GitHub.

## McGraw Hill — Remote (since COVID), previously Seattle, WA

### Principal Engineer, Cloud Center of Excellence (January 2024—October 2024)

- Assumed a role influencing the technical direction of the entire organization. Ensured a focus on real-world, actionable feedback and provided strategic direction aligned with practical needs.
- Continued to be involved in the oversight and direction of our AWS stack, security, guardrails, and more.
- Identified opportunities to extend the security measures and guardrails developed for AWS to other cloud platforms.

### Principal Cloud and Platform Engineer (June 2020—January 2024)

- Transitioned from Engineering Manager to a strategic technical leadership role.
- Managed the program for building and maintaining base AMIs for all of McGraw Hill.
- Using <u>AWS SDKs</u>, conducted comprehensive scans of Route 53 to obtain a mapping of thousands of active websites owned by McGraw Hill. Focused on identifying and remediating misconfigurations, rotating certificates, and more.
- Rebuilt our <u>Artifactory</u> cluster with a "cattle, not pets" approach. Ran the project from inception to completion, including the majority of development. Worked across dozens of teams and hundreds of services to complete the project.

### Engineering Manager, Site Reliability (October 2018—June 2020)

- Managed a team of four, while working to level-up the team's technical skills and leadership capabilities. Conducted regular 1:1s, performance reviews, and career development discussions.
- Led the <u>Site Reliability Engineering</u> (SRE) team in addressing macro-oriented problems affecting decentralized, heterogeneous engineering teams across the company. Empowered greater self-service for engineering teams.
- Revamped the Seattle SRE interview process to prioritize a 70/30 focus on software engineering (Dev) and systems operations (Ops).
   Emphasized leadership qualities, bias for action, and high curiosity.
- Owned and served as the key decision-maker in development of a core platform for company-wide, reliability-focused projects.
- Formed and led a leadership group to establish a process maintaining reusable Terraform modules which could be composed together according to a service's needs.
- Customized the Amazon Linux AMIs to comply with Level-2 <u>CIS</u> Guidelines for both Amazon Linux and <u>Docker</u>. Collaborated closely
  with cybersecurity, operations, and various business units to ensure compliance.
- Developed custom security and operational tooling where off-the-shelf tools wouldn't give us what we needed, to understand the current posture of ±200 AWS accounts.
- Reduced the time to deploy a new service from dozens of weeks to a single meeting by implementing a *Monitoring-as-Code* methodology, and defining broad-use <u>Service Level Objectives</u> (SLOs).

#### Staff Software Engineer (October 2016—October 2018)

- Led the development of multiple Tier-1 services within the educational content authoring pipeline, leveraging technologies such as REST, GraphQL, API design, Amazon ECS, Docker, Terraform, ePubs, and security best practices.
- Provided the technical direction of these projects, promoted their adoption across the organization, provided comprehensive documentation, and offered ongoing guidance on adoption.
- Led the development of the authoring component of <u>McGraw Hill's SmartBook 2.0 product</u>, and the internal system which indexes authored content, builds ePubs, and encodes images/video for McGraw Hill's ePub CDN.
- Introduced the adoption of continuous integration (CI), continuous delivery (CD), rapid deployment practices, and Docker containers.
- Introduced a more hands-on monitoring approach, enabling development teams to actively engage in their own operations. Achieved significantly lower *Mean Time to Recovery* (MTTR).
- Served as a core resource in adopting Infrastructure-as-Code (IaC) tools such as Terraform and Packer.

# WePay — Redwood City, CA

#### DevOps Engineer (April 2015—September 2016)

- Led a cross-company initiative to upgrade the monolithic application from PHP 5.4 to PHP 5.6 (the latest at the time). Facilitated cross-team collaboration among all major engineering teams and QA departments in order to achieve results.
- Initiated a program to automate the creation of base server images for our cloud servers. They allowed new servers to boot and begin serving traffic ~75% faster.
- Began investigating ways to implement configuration-as-code for our cloud infrastructure.

#### Senior API Engineer (April 2014—April 2015)

- Took the lead on the company's HackerOne program, coordinating across teams to address security issues.
- Built a development environment for engineering teams. Reduced new engineer onboarding time from 2 weeks → 1 day.
- Instrumental in designing WePay's MFA-as-a-Service offering. (U.S. patent filing US15042104)
- Developed new API endpoints to help expand WePay's business and support its partners.

#### Amazon Web Services — Seattle, WA

#### Web Development Engineer II (March 2010-April 2014)

- AWS hard-forked my open-source CloudFusion project into the AWS SDK for PHP, then hired me to work on it.
- Collaborated with the <u>AWS Elastic Beanstalk</u> team to provide PHP support for the platform, which launched in March 2012.
- Played a key role in the creation and development of the <u>AWS SDK for PHP</u> v2, incorporating significant changes in the PHP language and community since CloudFusion was first written in 2005.
- Collaborated with the AWS Design team on the <u>AWS Management Console</u>, to build a robust and user-friendly console. Led one of the first teams to provide reusable UI building blocks at AWS.
- Focusing on Amazon's *Customer Obsession* leadership principle, I successfully pushed for being better stewards of our community. Included increased transparency, better communication, and improved tooling for developers. [Examples]

# **Projects**

Proof that I can code, call APIs, interact with SDKs, and build user-facing software. I have live-coding anxiety, so live-coding interviews will always present me at my worst, not my best.

- **DevSec Tools:** Building a <u>website</u>, <u>CLI tool</u>, <u>and Go library</u> for helping developers identify potential web security configuration issues (in-progress).
- Custom Linux Packages: Building a repository of custom Linux packages (in-progress).
- CSP Evaluator: Building a parser and evaluator for Content Security Policy (CSP) directives in Go (in-progress).

- Terraform Provider: Built a custom provider which provides a set of utility functions for use in Terraform/OpenTofu.
- Multi-Platform Docker: Built a downloader for GitHub release assets which simplifies building multi-platform images.
- AWS Organization Security: Built a <u>library + CLI tool</u> which simplifies the AWS pattern for multi-account organizations which they call "hub and spoke."
- AWS Session Manager: The terminal is the right tool for shell sessions. Built a <u>TUI</u> for <u>simplifying connections to SSM-enabled EC2</u> <u>instances</u> using your Terminal.
- Configuration for tflint: Built a tool for generating up-to-date configurations for AWS/GCP/Azure for use with tflint.

### Recommendations

See a selective list of recommendations from co-workers and peers.

# **Groups and Accomplishments**

- U.S. patent filing, "System and Methods for User Authentication across Multiple Domains" (US15042104) (2016)
- U.S. patent filing, "Hive-based Peer-to-Peer Network" (US8103870B2) (2007)
- Voting representative for AWS, PHP Framework Interoperability Group (2012–2013)

# **Keywords and Skills**

This list is not exhaustive, but is targeted toward the skills most relevant to Software Engineering and DevTools roles.

API design, API versioning, CLI tools, <u>Bash</u>, <u>CircleCI</u>, <u>Docker</u>, <u>GitHub Actions</u>, <u>Git</u>, <u>Go</u>, <u>GraphQL</u>, <u>JWT</u>, <u>NFS</u>, <u>PHP</u> (modern), <u>Python</u>, <u>REST</u>, <u>Redis</u>, <u>Subversion</u>, <u>Vagrant</u>, <u>WordPress</u>, <u>XSLT</u>, <u>ffmpeg</u>, <u>twelve-factor applications</u>, automation, building platforms, code generation, defensive cybersecurity, multi-platform development, performance, scalability, software library design, software testing, technical documentation.

### **Education**

Obtained a **Bachelor of Arts** degree in *Design and Visualization* from *Silicon Valley College* (now <u>Carrington College</u>) in San Jose, CA.

Graduated in November 2003 with a 3.84 GPA.